CAITLIN SUSAN TENISON

Soar Technology, Inc. caitlin.tenison@soartech.com | Research Scientist | www.ctenison.com

BIO

Dr. Caitlin Tenison has over 10 years' experience in Cognitive Neuroscience studying the neural underpinnings of higher-order cognition. Her research focuses on identifying the learning mechanisms and cognitive changes that underlie the acquisition of cognitive skill. She has experience analysing EEG, MEG, and fMRI brain imaging modalities both using traditional signal processing approaches and extending machine learning methods to detect latent cognitive states and cope with rich time-series data. Her work is characterized by the use of multi-modal data to provide convergent evidence of the state of an individual. She also has experience designing research studies, using cognitive behavioral test-batteries, and working with diverse patient populations.

<u>Keywords:</u> Cognitive Modeling, Skill Acquisition, Problem Solving, Science of Learning, Data-mining

EDUCATION

2016- 2017 Postdoctoral Researcher

Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA

Supervisor. Dr. John R. Anderson

2011- 2016 Ph.D. in Psychology

Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA

Affiliations: Program for Interdisciplinary Education Research,

Pittsburgh Science of Learning Center

Advisor. Dr. John R. Anderson

Committee: Dr. Robert Siegler & Dr. Marcel Just

2005-2009 B.A. in Psychology and Plan II Honors

University of Texas, Austin, TX

GPA 4.0 Cum Laude Ampla et Magna

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Articles

Tenison, C., Fincham, J., & Anderson, J. (2016). Phases of learning: How skill acquisition impacts cognitive processing. *Cognitive Psychology.* 87,1-28.

Jolles, D., Supekar, K., Richardson, J., Tenison, C., Ashkenazi, S., Rosenberg-Lee, M., Fuchs, L., & Menon, V. (2016). Reconfiguration of parietal circuits with cognitive tutoring in elementary school children. *Cortex. 83, 231-245.*

- Jolles, D., Wassermann D., Chokani, R., Richardson, J., Tenison, C., Bammer, R., Supekar, K. Menon, V. (2016). Plasticity of left perisylvian white-matter tracts is associated with individual differences in math learning. *Brain Structure and Function*. 221(3), 1337-1351.
- Tenison, C., & Anderson, J. (2015). Modeling the distinct phases of skill acquisition. *Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition.* 42(5), 749-767.
- Iuculano, T., Rosenberg-Lee, M., Richardson, J., Tenison, C., Fuchs, L., Supekar, K., & Menon, V. (2015). Cognitive tutoring induces widespread neuroplasticity and remediates brain function in children with mathematical learning disabilities. *Nature Communications*, 6.
- Tenison, C., Fincham, J., & Anderson, J. (2014). Detecting math problem solving strategies. An investigation into the use of retrospective self-reports, latency and fMRI data. *Neuropsychologia*, 54, 41-52.
- Supekar, K., Swigart, A., Tenison, C., Jolles, D., Rosenberg-Lee, M., Fuchs, L., & Menon, V. (2013). Neural predictors of individual differences in response to math tutoring in primary-grade school children. *PNAS.* 11(20), 8230-8235.
- White, M. P., Shirer, W. R., Molfino, M. J., Tenison, C., Damoiseaux, J. S., & Greicius, M. D. (2013). Disordered reward processing and functional connectivity in trichotillomania: a pilot study. *Journal of Psychiatric Research*, 47(9), 1264-1272.
- Ashkenazi, S., Rosenberg-Lee, M., Tenison, C., & Menon, V. (2012). Weak task-related modulation and stimulus representations during arithmetic problem solving in children with developmental dyscalculia. *Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience*, 2(1), 152-166.

Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers

- Tenison, C., & Anderson, J. (2017, July). *Impact of practice frequency on learning and retention.* Presented at the 39th Conference of the Cognitive Science Society, London, UK
- Popov, V., Ostarek, M. & Tenison, C.(2017, July). *Inferential pittfalls in decoding neural representations*. Presented at the 39th Conference of the Cognitive Science Society, London, UK
- Tenison, C. (2016, June). *Modeling the phases of skill acquisition*. Presented at the 4th annual Advances in Cognitive Systems: Students of Cognitive Systems Workshop, Evanston, IL.

- Tenison, C., & MacLellan, C. J. (2015, June). *The Impact of Instructional Intervention and Practice on Help-Seeking Strategies within an ITS*. In Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Educational Data Mining, Madrid, Spain.
- Tenison, C. & Anderson, J. (2014, July). *Detecting Changes in Math Strategy During Learning*. In Proceedings of the 36th Conference of the Cognitive Science Society, Quebec City, Canada.
- Tenison, C., & MacLellan, C. J. (2014, June). *Modeling Strategy Use in an Intelligent Tutoring System: Implications for Strategic Flexibility.* In Proceedings of the 12th International Intelligent Tutoring Systems, Honolulu, HI.
- Tenison, C., & Anderson, J. (2014, June). *An Exploration of Two Methods for using fMRI to identify Student Problem Solving Strategies*. In Proceedings of Workshop "Utilizing EEG Input in Intelligent Tutoring Systems" at the 12th International Intelligent Tutoring Systems, Honolulu, HI.

Conference Presentations

- Tenison, C., & Anderson, J. (2016, August). From computation to automization: How practice alters initial neural response to familiar arithmetic problems. Presented at the 38th Conference of the Cognitive Science Society, Philadelphia, PA.
- Tenison, C., & Anderson, J. (2015, May). *Exploring skill acquisition with cognitive and brain-based models*. Paper presented at the 8th annual Inter-Science of Learning Center Student and Post-Doc Conference, San Diego, CA.
- Tenison, C., & Anderson, J. (2013, June). *Detecting math problem solving strategies using retrospective self-reports, latency, and fMRI data.* Presented at the Organization for Human Brain Mapping, Seattle, WA.
- Tenison, C., & Anderson, J. (2013, February). *Assessing strategy use in a fMRI study of arithmetic training*. Presented at the Inter-Science of Learning Center Student and Post-Doc Conference, Philadelphia, PA.
- Rosenberg-Lee, M., Escovar, E., Tenison, C., Khouzam, A., & Menon, V. (2012, October). Dynamic changes in brain response and connectivity associated with arithmetic fact learning in children. Presented at Society for Neuroscience, New Orleans, LA.
- Jolles, D., Rosenberg-Lee, M., Ashkenazi, S., Supekar, K., Tenison, C., Duan, X., Uddin, L., Fuchs, L., & Menon, V. (2012, October). *Math training strengthens intrinsic connectivity of parietal cortex in children*. Presented at Society for Neuroscience, New Orleans, LA.

- Rosenberg-Lee, M., Escovar, E., Tenison, C., Khouzam, A., & Menon, V. (2012, August). *How do children learn math facts?* Presented at EARLI SIG Neuroscience and Education, London, UK.
- Jolles, D., Rosenberg-Lee, M., Supekar, K., Tenison, C., Ashkenazi, S., Duan, X., & Menon, V. (2012, August). Math training changes intrinsic brain connectivity of the intraparietal sulcus. Presented at EARLI SIG Neuroscience and Education, London, UK.
- Rosenberg-Lee, M., Young, C., Tenison, C., Geary, D., & Menon, V. (2010, June). *Neural Correlates of Developmental Dyscalculia in Children: Univariate and Multivariate Analysis.*Presented at Human Brain Mapping Annual Meeting, Barcelona, SP.
- Pacheco, J., Dailey, N., Olivares, M., Tenison, C., & Schnyer, D. (2009, March) *An fMRI examination of the Effects of Aging on Memory Monitoring for Source and Item Recognition.* Presented at Cognitive Neuroscience Society Meeting, San Francisco, CA.
- Trujillo, L., Tenison, C., Dailey, D., & Schnyer, D. (2009, March). An ERP Examination of the Differential Effects of Sleep Deprivation on Endogenously Cued and Exogenously Cued Attention. Presented at Cognitive Neuroscience Society Meeting, San Francisco, CA.
- Goldwater, M., Schnyer, D., Markman, A., Williams, V., Tenison, C., & Dailey, N. (2008, April) *An Event Related Potential Analysis of Novel Denominal Verb Interpretation*. Presented at Cognitive Neuroscience Society Meeting, San Francisco, CA.

Manuscripts in Progress

- Tenison, C., Fincham, J., & Anderson, J. (In prep). From computation to automization: How practice alters initial neural response to familiar arithmetic problems.
- Anderson, J., Borst, J., Fincham, J., Ghuman, A., Tenison, C., & Qiong, Z. (In prep). The temporal structure of memory retrieval.

GRANTS RECEIVED

2014-2015

National Science Foundation, Science of Learning Centers. Award No. SMA-1430662. (Co-Author with Chris MacLellan and Audrey Kittredge) Conference: A Proposal to the National Science Foundation for Support of the Seventh Annual Inter-Science of Learning Centers (iSLC) Student / Postdoctoral Scholar Conference

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2011-2017 ACT-R Laboratory

Carnegie Mellon University

Dr. John R. Anderson, Principal Investigator

Researching methods for modeling cognition by combining multiple sources of data with specific focus on detecting cognitive changes

due to skill acquisition using brain and behavioral data

2013-2015 Interdisciplinary Independent Project

Carnegie Mellon University

Collaboration with Christopher MacLellan, PhD student Developing a domain general data-mining technique that can identify strategy use and strategic flexibility using student interactions with intelligent tutoring system software

2009-2011 Social Science Research Assistant

Stanford Cognitive and Systems Neuroscience Laboratory

Stanford University

Dr. Vinod Menon, Principal Investigator

Designed and conducted an NIH-funded study of the neural effects of math remediation on children with math learning disabilities

2008-2009 Undergraduate Research

Undergraduate Honors Program University of Texas at Austin

Dr. Charles Holahan and Dr. David Schnyer, Advisors
Designed and implemented experiment investigating the
interdependence between the neural networks of music and
language through priming word recognition using familiar songs

2007-2009 Research Assistant

Schnyer Lab

University of Texas at Austin

Working with Dr. David Schnyer and Jennifer Pacheco

Studied the effects of aging on memory monitoring using fMRI

Working with Dr. David Schnyer and Dr. Logan Trujillo

Studied the differential effects of sleep deprivation on cued attention

using Electrophysiology (EEG)

Working with Dr. David Schnyer and Micah Goldwater

Used EEG to study how people interpret and understand novel

denominal verbs

SKILLS

Analysis Packages Matlab, R, and SPSS.

Statistical Skills Data mining techniques (e.g., hidden Markov modeling, linear

discriminant analysis, principal components analysis), regression,

hierarchical linear modeling, Bayesian modeling

Research Methods Designing experiments, administering and scoring neuropsychological

evaluations, working with participants between ages 7 – 80 years old, recruiting and scheduling subjects, cognitive task analysis, managing

lab, overseeing and mentoring research assistants

Brain Imaging Methods Collecting functional, structural and diffusion tensor imaging (DTI)

scans using a G.E. 3.0-tesla MRI magnet

Collecting magnetoencephalography (MEG) data

Analyzing fMRI data using software packages: AFNI and FSL and SPM

Analyzing MEG data using MNE

72-channel electrophysiology (EEG) recording with the BioSemi

System

HONORS AND AWARDS

2016 Conference Travel Grant

National Science Foundation

For attendance of the 4th annual Advances in Cognitive Systems

Conference

2016 Bobby Klatzky Graduate Student Publication Award

Carnegie Mellon University

Given annually for outstanding performance in scholarly research and

writing.

2015 Latin American School for Education, Cognitive, and Neural Sciences

The James S. McDonnell Foundation

Selected to attend a two-week international meeting of students and faculty to discuss bridging between education and brain sciences.

2015 Dick Hayes Graduate Student Service Award

Carnegie Mellon University

Given annually to the graduate student who contributes time and

service to the department

2011 San Francisco Regional MENSA Scholarship

San Francisco Regional MENSA

Funding provided for attending graduate school

2008-2009 The Undergraduate Research Fellowship & Undergraduate Honors

Research Grant

University of Texas at Austin

Provides research funding for undergraduate research projects

2005-2009 Terry Scholar

University of Texas at Austin

Full academic scholarship for four years of college

SERVICE

2015-2016 PIER Graduate Student Representative

Program for Interdisciplinary Education Research

Represented the graduate students at the Steering Committee

meetings

2013-2014 Conference Organizer

Inter-Science of Learning Center Student and Postdoc Conference Organized and hosted the 7th Annual iSLC conference in Pittsburgh bringing together students from Science of Learning Centers from

across the United States

2013-2014 Organizer of Brain and Machine Learning Meetings

Collaboration between Psychology and Machine Learning Organized series of talks to foster dialogue between Machine

Learning and Psychology Departments

2013-2014 PIER Speaker Series Organizer

Program for Interdisciplinary Education Research Invited and organized guest speakers series

2012-2013 President

Pittsburgh Science of Learning Center Student Group

Organized meetings, professional development, and attended executive committee meetings as representative for graduate

students of the PSLC

2011-2012 Student Committee Member

Carnegie Mellon University - Human Computer Interaction Institute Involved in planning curricula and requirements for the Masters in Educational Technology and Applied Learning Science program